<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="en">
  <title>Reuben Son | Reflections at Recurse Center</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <link href="https://reubenson.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://reubenson.com"/>
  <updated>2023-11-05T17:23:18Z</updated>
  <id>https://reubenson.com</id>
  <author>
    <name>Reuben Son</name>
    <email>reubenson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Week 1 at Recurse Center</title>
    <link href="https://reubenson.com/recurse/week-1/"/>
    <updated>2023-11-05T17:23:18Z</updated>
    <id>https://reubenson.com/recurse/week-1/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Week 1 at Recurse Center&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twice this year, I&#39;ve had the good fortune to find myself in spaces filled with people aligned to a common purpose: earlier this year at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haystack-mtn.org/&quot;&gt;Haystack Mountain Schoool of Craft&lt;/a&gt;, and now at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.recurse.com/&quot;&gt;Recurse Center&lt;/a&gt;. These environments foster a regime of expansion and change, and have the power to focus, broaden, and alter one&#39;s sense of purpose. These environments can be quite intense to adjust and recalibrate to, as they involve large changes to the core substrates and infrastructures that compose of one&#39;s daily existence: time, geography, architecture, and community. Much of this is self-evident and not particularly profound to point out, but its lived experience can most immediately be felt in the constellation of affective states that manifest throughout the transition: overhwelm, nervous excitement, disorientation, decision paralysis, fight-or-flight, hyperactivity, dissociation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer, at Haystack, in addition to learning the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@reubenson/foray-into-3d-printing-with-clay-at-haystack-207064511cd&quot;&gt;workflows and processes of ceramic 3D printing&lt;/a&gt;, I went paddleboarding for the very first time. On my initial attempts to stand up and paddle about, I was quickly tossed into the water. The Haystack campus is built on a granite island off the Maine coast, and faces out directly to the ocean. After falling a couple times into the rocking waves, I decided to paddle sitting down instead for a while, but before finally returning to shore, I decided to just stand on the board for a bit, without paddling. I then sat back down again and rowed back to shore. The next day, and each subsequent day on the beach, I found myself immediately able to paddleboard standing up without any further issue. The last time I watched my body in the process of learning was when I began taking ceramics classes in 2019, and it struck me, more or less for the first time, how quickly, and quietly, embodied intelligence is set into motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think of acclimating to environments like Recurse in a similar way, that the transition still passes through the body, even for something as heady as Recurse&#39;s guiding mission to enable its participants to become radically better programmers over the duration of the residency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;divider-line&quot;&gt;〜〜〜&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it&#39;s been a lot of just that, riding the waves through varying affective states, while also slowly refining my sense of purpose here. I&#39;ve been working out a set of priorities and goals, in order to make more tangible that sense of purpose, which I&#39;ll share below. It&#39;s a little sobering that after having just wrapped the first week of my six-week residency here, I&#39;m already nearly a quarter of the way through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I&#39;ve committed to going through some amount of &lt;a href=&quot;https://karpathy.ai/zero-to-hero.html&quot;&gt;Andrej Karpathy&#39;s introduction to building neural networks from scratch&lt;/a&gt; and Russell Webb&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Russ741/karpathy-nn-z2h&quot;&gt;accompanying worksheets&lt;/a&gt;, though I&#39;m also likely going to switch to or ping-pong between that series and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fastai/fastbook&quot;&gt;Fast.ai series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Guiding principles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay open-ended and cultivate sensitivity, paying attention to what drives my own interests in tech, and see what it is that drives other programmers to similar or divergent interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of the residency as more of an onboarding, not an end to itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embrace being process-oriented, balanced against being results-driven (but not necessarily working backwards from a predetermined outcome)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Goals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn a new programming language (Python)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn the fundamentals of ML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get feedback on previous/existing projects, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://frogchor.us/&quot;&gt;Frog Chorus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish and share at least one small project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand current employment landscape / opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give focus to both writing code and text (like this entry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>